[Waco] Branch Davidians: Bill Pitts papers, Inclusive: 1963-2001, undated, Bulk: 1993-1994
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
[Waco] Branch Davidians: Bill Pitts papers
Inclusive: 1963-2001, undated, Bulk: 1993-1994
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
3890
Pitts, William "Bill", 1937 -
2 document boxes.
The [Waco] Branch Davidians: Bill Pitts papers contains materials produced and collected by Bill Pitts, a professor in the Religion Department at Baylor University. The materials primarily cover the Branch Davidians siege of 1993.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
The religious sects known as the Davidians and Branch Davidians were the products of a reform movement within the Seventh-Day Adventist Church. Problems began when a group of Adventists, led by Bulgarian immigrant Victor Houteff, began to challenge the traditional hierarchy of the denomination. Houteff claimed to have received personal revelations from God and published his controversial views in a book entitled The Shepherd's Rod (1932). Houteff and his followers, the Davidians, believed that the spiritual gift of prophecy was necessary for effective leadership so that King David's earthly kingdom could be re-established on earth prior to the second coming of Jesus Christ. After the leaders of the Seventh-Day Adventist Church excommunicated his sect, Houteff moved to Waco, Texas, and continued to preach until his death in 1955.
Leadership among the Davidians fragmented afterwards, with Victor's widow Florence Houteff and Benjamin Roden vying for control. The group that followed Benjamin Roden and his wife Lois would later be known as the Branch Davidians. The Rodens led the Branch Davidians for several decades, but the 1980s brought about further division within the sect. A newcomer named Vernon Howell had joined the Branch Davidians in 1981. Three years later, a schism occurred within the Branch Davidians, with Howell leading his own group of followers to a new site in Palestine, Texas. Through a series of confrontations between Howell and George Roden, the son of Benjamin and Lois Roden, control of the Branch Davidians' headquarters in Waco passed to Howell, who legally changed his name to David Koresh in 1990.
Rumors concerning polygamy, abuse, and arms-dealing within the Branch Davidian group aroused the suspicions of the federal government. Thus, federal agencies such as the Federal Bureau of Investigation and the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives began to monitor the group. In response to a stockpiling of illegal weapons, the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives secured a search warrant for the investigation of the Branch Davidians' compound near Waco, Texas. From 1993 February 28 until April 19, Branch Davidians under the leadership of David Koresh resisted federal agents' attempts to storm their Mount Carmel Center. The fifty-day siege ended when the compound erupted in flames, killing David Koresh and most of his followers.
William “Bill” Lee Pitts, the donor of the collection, is currently a professor in Baylor University’s Religion Department. Pitts earned his B.A. at Baylor in 1960, majoring in both history and religion. He then went on to earn a Master of Divinity at Vanderbilt Divinity School and his Ph.D. in religion at Vanderbilt University (1969). He currently teaches church history at the graduate student level. Pitts has long been considered an expert concerning the Davidian and Branch Davidian sects.
Scope and Content
The [Waco] Branch Davidians: Bill Pitts papers spans from 1963 to 2001, but the bulk of the materials does focus on the immediate aftermath of the Waco siege (1993-1994). Literary productions, series II, is by far the largest in the collection and contains scholarly articles and essays about the Davidians and Branch Davidians as well as the American public's response to the tragedy.
Arrangement
The [Waco] Branch Davidians: Bill Pitts papers lacked any initial organization or accompanying inventory when donated to The Texas Collection.
After initial appraisal, an inventory of the remaining archival materials was compiled. The collection now consists of four series organized by type: I. Correspondence, II. Literary Productions, III. Photographic Materials, and IV. Audio Recordings.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3890. Acquired 2013-07-08
Related Resources
Items in related collections
William "Bill" Pitts Papers
[Waco] Branch Davidians: Ron Armstrong collection, Inclusive: 1931-1960, undated, Bulk: 1931-1933
[Waco] Branch Davidians: "The Facts About Mt. Carmel" Exhibit collection, Inclusive: 1961-2004, undated, Bulk: 1993-1994
[Waco] Branch Davidians: Robert F. Darden III collection, Inclusive: 1932-1993, undated, Bulk:1985-1993, undated
[Waco] Branch Davidians: William Smith collection, Inclusive: 1984-1998, undated, Bulk: 1993-1995
[Waco] Branch Davidians: Mark Swett collection, Inclusive: 1921-2001, undated, Bulk: 1978-1993
[Waco] Branch Davidians: "Turning Point at Waco"
[Waco] Branch Davidians: Amo Paul Roden papers, Inclusive: 1946-2008, 2017, undated, Bulk: 1993-2003
[Waco] Branch Davidians: Don Marion, circa 1980s-1990s
[Waco] Branch Davidians: Kenneth G.C. Newport
[Waco] Branch Davidians: Kirk D. Lyons collection, Inclusive: 1979-1998, undated, Bulk: 1993-1995
[Waco] Branch Davidians: Maury Povich Show
[Waco] Branch Davidians: Mount Carmel Seventh Day Adventist collection, Inclusive: 1938-1998, undated, Bulk: 1959-1961; 1996-1997
[Waco] Branch Davidians: FBI Letters and Negotiation Transcripts collection, Inclusive: 1993
[Waco] Branch Davidians: Matthew D. Wittmer Collection
[Waco] Branch Davidians: Joe Robert collection, Inclusive: 1932-1997, undated, Bulk: 1979-1995
Related references
Kerstetter, Todd. “That’s Just the American Way: The Branch Davidian Tragedy and Western Religious History.” Western Historical Quarterly vol. 35, no. 4 (2004 Winter): 453-471.
Lawson, Ronald. “Seventh-Day Adventist Responses to Branch Davidian Notoriety: Patterns of Diversity within a Sect Reducing Tension with Society.” Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion vol. 34, no. 3 (1995 September): 323-341.
“Local Man Offers Insight into Waco.” Religion News Report vol. 4, no. 223 (2000 July 4). Accessed July 12, 2013.
Pitts, William L. "Davidians and Branch Davidians." Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2013 July 12.
“William L. Pitts, Jr.” Baylor University. Accessed 2013 July 12.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Branch Davidians.
Places
Waco (Tex.) -- History -- 20th Century.
Subjects
Baylor University -- Faculty.; Waco Branch Davidian Disaster, Tex., 1993.
Genres
Articles.; Correspondence.; Interviews (Sound recordings); Periodicals.; Programs.; Research notes.
- Correspondence, 1993-1994, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains three folders of correspondence written to and from Dr. Bill Pitts. The materials are almost exclusively dealing with the Branch Davidian crisis of 1993.
  - General, 1993 March-June 19 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General, 1993 June 21-September 14 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General, 1993 September 15-1994, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Literary Productions, 1963-2001, undated; 2
  This series, the largest in the collection, contains approximately three boxes worth of materials written and compiled by Bill Pitts. The major focus of the articles and notes is the Waco siege, but also included in the series are student exams from Dr. Pitts' classes and some pamphlets and programs produced by Baylor University.
  - Article: The American Scholar: “The Ph.D. Squid”: Theodore Ziolkowski, 1990 March 23 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Article: The Atlantic Monthly: “Illiberal Education”: Dinesh D’Souza, 1991 March (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Article: Christian Spirituality Bulletin: “Spirituality and the Process of History”: Philip Sheldrake, 1993 Spring (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Article: The Council of Societies for the Study of Religion: “The Davidian Tradition”: Bill Pitts, 1993 November (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Article: Docket Call: “The Long Arm of the Law and the Right Hand of God”: Alan Hunt, 1993 Fall (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Article: Ethics & International Affairs: “The Decline of International Studies”: Kenneth Thompson, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Article: Journal of Alternative Religion and Culture: “The Mount Carmel Davidians: Adventist Reformers, 1935-1959”: Bill Pitts, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Article: New York Times: “Why the Flames of Waco Won’t Die”: Richard Schweder, 1994 April 17 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Article: Soldier of Fortune: “A Blundering Inferno”: James Pate, 1993 July (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Articles: Soldier of Fortune, 1993 June (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Biographical Materials: Curriculum Vitae: Bill Pitts, circa 1993 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Book: Travesty: A True Crime Story, The Du Pont Kidnap Case and the LaRouche Railroad, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Clippings: General, 1993-1999 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Clippings: General, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Essay: “The Holy Spirit, She”: Lois Roden, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Essay: “Lessons from Waco: When Will We Ever Learn?”: James Richardson, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Essay: “The Mount Carmel Davidians: Adventist Reformers, 1935-1959”: Bill Pitts, 1991 November (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Essay: “Why Did Waco Happen?”: Larry Shinn, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Newsletters: General, 1993 May-June (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Newsletters: General, 1993 October, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Notepad: General, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Notes: General (1 of 2), 1993-1994, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Notes: General (2 of 2), 1993-1994, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Notes: Bonnie Haldeman, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Notes: Editorial Comments Concerning David Koresh’s “Decoded Message of the Seven Seals”, 1993 October 4 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Notes: Phone Interview with Don Adair, 1993 November (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Notes: Waco Tribune-Herald Articles, 1993 April 8-9 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Pamphlet: “The Baptist Faith and Message”: Southern Baptist Convention, 1963 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Periodical: The Baptist Standard, 1993 April 7 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Periodical: Executive Intelligence Review, 1993 October 22 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Periodical: Freedom: Church of Scientology, 1993 May (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Periodical: Shekinah, 1980 December (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Periodical: Shekinah, 1981 February (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Preliminary Examination: Drew Shofner, 1992 Spring (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Preliminary Examination: Scott Moore (1 of 2), 1992 Spring (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Preliminary Examination: Scott Moore (2 of 2), 1992 Spring (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Program: Independence Association, 2001 June 3 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Programs: Baylor University in England, 1992-1994 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Proposals: Baylor University: World Affairs Minor, 1991 May (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Syllabus: Introduction to Church History: Bill Pitts, 1999 Fall (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Photographic Materials, undated; 3
  This series, the smallest in the collection, contains a single photograph of a sign from Deliverance Today Ministries.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photographic print
  - Photograph: Deliverance Today Ministries, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Audio Recordings, 1993; 4
  This series contains four audio cassette tapes in which Bill Pitts addressed a Rotary Club concerning the Davidians. The tapes were created in the midst of the fifty-day siege of the Mount Carmel Center.
  Cassette tape
  - Cassette Tape: “Dr. Bill Pitts - The Davidians”: The Rotary Club (1 of 4), 1993 April 2 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Cassette Tape: “Dr. Bill Pitts - The Davidians”: The Rotary Club (2 of 4), 1993 April 2 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Cassette Tape: “Dr. Bill Pitts - The Davidians”: The Rotary Club (3 of 4), 1993 April 2 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Cassette Tape: “Dr. Bill Pitts - The Davidians”: The Rotary Club (4 of 4), 1993 April 2 (Box 2, Folder 13)